A Guide to the Additional Michael Ryan Papers, 1968-1989
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Additional Michael Ryan Papers 1968-1989
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10963-a
This collection consists of 1,675 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access is controlled by the depositor or his designee. Those wishing access to the collection must furnish the Director of Special Collections a memorandum outlining their academic background, scope of project, importance of this collection to that project and any publication plans. The Director will forward the request to the depositor or, in his absence, his designee, Doreen Gildroy.
Acquisition Information
Michael Ryan of Santa Monica, California, loaned this addition to his papers to the Library through Charles Verrill, Liz Darhansoff Agency, New York, New York, on September 4, 1991, without restrictions.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the papers of poet Michael Ryan of Santa Monica, California, contain ca. 1,675 items (9 Hollinger boxes, ca. 4 linear feet), ca. 1968-1989, and include manuscripts and typescripts of his poetry; notes; lectures; articles; correspondence; printed matter; teaching materials used in Ryan's literature and poetry classes at Southern Methodist University and Goddard College, and manuscripts by other poets.
Arrangement
The first series of manuscripts by Michael Ryan consists of poems, articles, lectures, and miscellaneous manuscripts. The poems form the first subseries and each poem with all of its various drafts is foldered separately and arranged alphabetically by title. Any drafts of poems found in the previous Ryan accession (10963) were interfiled in that collection to keep the various drafts together. The second subseries contains drafts and notes for many of the same articles and lectures found in accession # 10963, and two drafts of his book of poetry, In Winter. New items include an interview with Michael Ryan published in Fiction and notes concerning "Poets on Poetry: An Annotated Checklist" and "Rhythm and Prosody." Also present in this series are several screenplays and short stories by Michael Ryan.
The second series contains Ryan's teaching files for classes at Goddard College and Southern Methodist University, recommendations for students and colleagues, grant applications submitted by Ryan, contracts, letters concerning employment, biographical information, and printed material about Ryan's career.
Correspondence with other poets, colleagues, and friends comprises the third series. Correspondents who have written more than two or three letters have their own folder and are listed individually in the box listing. Other correspondents are filed in two general correspondence folders but are listed by name in the box listing.
The fourth series consists of manuscripts by other authors, including interviews with Robert Penn Warren and Robert Hass, and poems by Stephen Dobyns, Tess Gallagher, Reginald Gibbons, Louise Gluck, Robert Hass, Thomas Lux, and Dennis Schmitz.
Contents List
- Series I: Manuscripts by Michael Ryan
  - Subseries A: Poetry
    - Acceptance Speech n.d. (Box 1)
    - After n.d. (Box 1)
    - All the Time n.d. (Box 1)
    - Aubade n.d. (Box 1)
    - The Ballad of Modern American Poetry n.d. (Box 1)
    - The Black Hole n.d. (Box 1)
    - The Brain Asks Something of the Heart n.d. (Box 1)
    - But n.d. (Box 1)
    - A Changed Season n.d. (Box 1)
    - Cheap Death n.d. (Box 1)
    - The Days n.d. (Box 1)
    - Do Not Go Gentle Into That Sweet Miss/Ms. n.d. (Box 1)
    - Early Morning Fog In Vermont n.d. (Box 1)
    - Elegy for Any Old Aunt n.d. (Box 1)
    - Every Move n.d. (Box 1)
    - Gangster Dreams n.d. (Box 1)
    - The Great Dark n.d. (Box 1)
    - A History of Rooms n.d. (Box 1)
    - Hopeless n.d. (Box 1)
    - Human Abstract n.d. (Box 1)
    - The Incredible Foolishness n.d. (Box 1)
    - Irishmen n.d. (Box 1)
    - Judas n.d. (Box 1)
    - Lowell's Last Class n.d. (Box 1)
    - Memory n.d. (Box 1)
    - Multi-National Corporate Capitalism n.d. (Box 1)
    - Nameless n.d. (Box 1)
    - 1976 n.d. (Box 1)
    - No Comparison n.d. (Box 1)
    - No One n.d. (Box 1)
    - Now and Then(also entitled Untouched& Such Friends) n.d. (Box 1)
    - Old Man's Poem n.d. (Box 1)
    - An Old Story n.d. (Box 1)
    - One Last Elegy [post 1974] (Box 1)
    - Poem at Thirty [1976] (Box 1)
    - Poem in Which I Give Up the Nobel Prize n.d. (Box 1)
    - The Pure Lonliness n.d. (Box 1)
    - A Quick Day in the Country n.d. (Box 1)
    - The Realist n.d. (Box 1)
    - Roots n.d. (Box 1)
    - Sex n.d. (Box 1)
    - A Shadow of Pavese n.d. (Box 1)
    - A Shape for It n.d. (Box 1)
    - The Small Poem n.d. (Box 1)
    - Speaking n.d. (Box 1)
    - Stones n.d. (Box 1)
    - Teleological n.d. (Box 1)
    - This Should Make An Internal Landscape n.d. (Box 1)
    - To Tell You the Truth n.d. (Box 1)
    - Two Looks at Time n.d. (Box 1)
    - Waking At Night n.d. (Box 1)
    - Wet Streets n.d. (Box 1)
    - What We Live In Always n.d. (Box 1)
    - Where I'll Be Good n.d. (Box 1)
    - Why n.d. (Box 1)
    - You Can Think n.d. (Box 1)
    - Untitled and Miscellaneous Poetry by Michael Ryan n.d. (Box 1)
  - Subseries B: Articles, Lectures, and other Manuscripts
    - Articles & Notes- Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 2)
    - Class Papers by Michael Ryan, chiefly at the University of Iowa and Claremont Graduate School ca. 1968-1971 (Box 2)
    - Disclosures of Poetry: A Lecture on Wallace Stevens& Notes (2 folders) [1982] (Box 2)
    - Eliot's Assumptions in Crazyhorse Poetry & Prose[1984] (Box 2)
    - TMs In Winter by Michael Ryan [ca. 1981] (Box 2)
    - TMs In Winter by Michael Ryan (Last Revision) [ca. 1981] (Box 2)
    - Interview with Michael Ryan in Fiction, with correspondence with Alison Kittrell ca. 1976 (Box 2)
    - On the Nature of Poetry- Notes & Drafts (2 folders) n.d. (Box 2)
    - Poets on Poetry: An Annotated checklist- Notes re a proposed anthology by Michael Ryan 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Rhythm and Prosody- Notes n.d. (Box 3)
    - Screenplays by Michael Ryan n.d. (Box 3)
    - Short Stories by Michael Ryan n.d. (Box 3)
    - Stanley Kunitz Article - Notes n.d. (Box 3)
    - A Talk on Wallace Stevens in Poetry[1979] (Box 3)
- Series II: Teaching Files & Miscellaneous Papers
  - Craft of Poetry Class taught by Michael Ryan 1975 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Reprints, Notes, Etc. 1976, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Goddard College MFA Writing Program: Tom Absher 1977 (Box 4)
  - Goddard College MFA Writing Program: Linda LaCombe (2 folders) [1976 ?]-1977 (Box 4)
  - Goddard College MFA Writing Program: Nancy Sherman Lewis 1978 (Box 4)
  - Goddard College MFA Writing Program: Hal Steven Shows 1978 (Box 4)
  - Grant Applications: National Endowment for the Humanities, John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, and National Endowment for the Arts 1976-1981 (Box 4)
  - Papers re Michael Ryan's Vita, Employment, and Contracts 1975-1978 (Box 4)
  - Printed and Miscellaneous Papers 1975-1981, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Recommendations 1975-1979 (Box 4)
  - Southern Methodist University: Discourse and Literature 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - Southern Methodist University Class on Poetry - Copies of Articles n.d. (Box 5)
  - Southern Methodist University: LS 2316 1976 (Box 5)
  - Southern Methodist University Graduate Seminar: Stevens and Roethke ca. 1974-1978, (4 folders) (Box 5)
- Series III: Correspondence
  - Correspondence: A-M 1974-1989 (Box 6)
    Correspondents include: Keith Althaus; William Arrowsmith; Ann Beattie; Jana Bradley; Michael Burbank; Mary Carter; Joan Cunliffe; Peter Davison; Norman Dubie; Betsy Dunn; Rubin Falk; Carolyn Forche; Jonathan Galassi; Reginald Gibbons; Jorie Graham; Russ Hall; David Mike Hamilton; Helen B. Harary; Sue Hartt; Robert Hass; Diane Johnson; Mary Karr; Elizabeth Kray; Marcia Lawther; Lois Lewis; Geraldine Little; Linda McCarriston; Jim McMichael; and Lisel Mueller
  - Correspondence: O-V 1977-1989 (Box 6)
    Correspondents include: Steve Orlen; Gregory Orr; Robert Pinsky; David Remnick; Nate Scaglione; Elinor Schmitz; Michael Sheridan; Martin Shockley; Maura Stanton; Jody Stewart; Leslie Z. Tobin; Robert Penn Warren; Robert H. Winner; Tobias Wolff; and Ellen Voigt
  - Correspondence: Stephen Berg 1979-1981, (18 items) (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Raymond Carver 1977-1981, (11 items) (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Stephen Dobyns 1977-1980, (6 items) (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Richard Ford 1977-1979, (16 items) (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Louise Gluck 1974-1980, n.d., (35 items) (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Donald Hall 1978-1981, (4 items) (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Holt, Rinehart and Winston 1979-1981, (18 items) (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Donald Justice 1976-1980, (17 items) (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Stanley Kunitz 1973-1980, (8 items) (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Thomas Lux 1974-1981, n.d., (26 items) (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Carol Muske 1981, (5 items) (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: John Frederick Nims 1979-1981, (11 items) (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Princeton University 1977-1980, (12 items) (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Publishers - Miscellaneous 1973-1980, n.d., (20 items) (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Ernest Sandeen 1974-1981, (24 items) (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Grace Schulman 1979-1980 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: John Skoyles 1974-1981, (53 items) (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: James Welsh 1976-1981, (4 items) (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Geoffrey Wolff 1977-1981, (16 items) (Box 8)
- Series IV: Manuscripts By Other Authors
  - A Conversation with Robert Penn Warren Transcript of an Interview with Bill Moyers 1976 Apr 4 (Box 9)
  - Awake and Walking(Thesis) by Catlyn Cage 1978 (Box 9)
  - Heat Death by Stephen Dobyns 1980 (Box 9)
  - Swing Shift An Original Screenplay by Nancy Dowd n.d. (Box 9)
  - Poems by Tess Gallagher n.d. (Box 9)
  - Poems by Reginald Gibbons n.d. (Box 9)
  - Poems by Louise Gluck 1974-1980 (Box 9)
  - Praise by Robert Hass 1979 (Box 9)
  - Interview with Robert Hass by Ceci Miller and Tracy Daugherty [post 1978] (Box 9)
  - The Livid Versus Silk by Thomas Lux n.d. (Box 9)
  - Goodwill, Inc. by Dennis Schmitz 1976 (Box 9)